<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain observations, vpon the new league or covenant as it was explained by a divine of the new assembly, in a congregation at London / written and sent unto him in a letter by some of his auditors, with copy of the said covenant.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7542</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11800757</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11800757</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49373</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31498)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49373)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 527:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain observations, vpon the new league or covenant as it was explained by a divine of the new assembly, in a congregation at London / written and sent unto him in a letter by some of his auditors, with copy of the said covenant.</title>
                  <author>Divine of the New Assembly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Rich. Harsell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Bristoll :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A Solemn League and Covenant, for reformation, and defence of religion, &amp;c.": p. 45-52.</note>
                  <note>Pages 27-32 and 40-41 have print show-through with some loss of text in filmed copy.  Pages 20-45 photographed from Bodleian Library copy and inserted at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Solemn League and Covenant (1643)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49373:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49373:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAIN OBSERVATIONS, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the New</hi> League or Covenant, As it was explained by a Divine of the New Aſſembly, in a Congregation at LONDON. VVritten and ſent unto him in a Letter by ſome of his Auditors. With a Copy of the ſaid COVENANT.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Ezek. 17.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Shall he Proſper? ſhall he eſcape that doth ſuch things? Or ſhall he break the Covenant, and be delivered?</p>
            </q>
            <p>BRISTOLL, Printed for <hi>Rich. Harſell,</hi> and are to be ſold by him in <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49373:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho: Briſtol.</signed>
               <date>
                  <hi>Feb.</hi> 20. 1643.</date>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49373:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Certain Obſervations, upon the new League or Covenant.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough it be a thing much to be pittied and lamented, to ſee and to hear daily, with what confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſome things of no ſmall concernment, ſuch as Oathes and Covenants, are preſſed upon mens Conſciences by ſome; and by others ſwallowed with as little ſtraining; yet it is not much to be wondred at. Temporall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects of profit, favour, credit, and worldly fears of diſcountenance, loſſes, perſecutions, by oppoſing the ſtream of times, have a ſtrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon mens proceedings, and provoke them to draw on in their attempts begun, though with galled Conſciences. And it is manifeſt from the holy Scripture, to be Gods way of taking ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon mens perverſneſſe; that when as (for atchieving of any end whatſoever) they will needs ſeek to ſtifle ſome evident light, and diſpence with ſome neceſſary parts of their obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience they are given up to ſtrong affections, whereby the heart is darkned, as with ſome miſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49373:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>caſt before them, the eyes ſometimes are. Now he that conſiders what force Imagination hath upon the body needs not think it ſtrange, that affection ſhould ſo far prevaile upon the minde, as to make a man miſtake the truth, to fore-judge the cauſe that he defends, and to venture upon every courſe, as juſt and lawfull, if it be expedient for promoting the deſigne; and may have ſome plauſible pretences and excuſes to bear it out. Which being ſo, we appeal to your ſelf, (or any conſidering man) whether it may not juſtly be preſumed, that in this matter of Oathes and Covenants (which we all know to be ſacred bonds, and to impoſe a ſtrong tye upon the conſcience) the eagerneſſe, yea, violence of ſome men in urging ſuch Oathes, doth proceed from their ſtrong affection to that cauſe, and their deep engagements for defence thereof: And then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the example of the chief Contrivers, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moters of theſe Oathes, (men perchance reputed of, amongſt the vulgar for their wiſdom, zeal, and piety) doth not prove juſtly Scandalous, to the weaker ſort, by drawing them into thoſe grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſinns, of raſh, unjuſt, or falſe ſwearing, whiles they relye upon theſe mens judgements, with too much eaſineſſe; or elſe are ſo much over-preſſed with the fear of ſome dammage, impriſonment, loſſe of goods and livelihood, that they are unawares, brought to do that, againſt which their conſcience findes reluctancy. If it were a thing hard to be believed, we could name you the men (for we have heard it from the mouthes of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49373:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>many) who can give no other reaſon for their entring into this preſent Covenant, beſides the fear of loſing all they have. Sir, we that preſent you with theſe lines, have ſadly thought on theſe things, and do from our hearts pitty the danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous eſtate of many thouſand ſoules, that by the example, and perſwaſions of Miniſters, and others in eſteem amongſt them, are driven into thoſe Bryers, which are likely, one day, ſorely to vex, and wound their Conſciences. And therefore out of the tenderneſſe we bear to our own ſouls, that we may not deprive our ſelves of that internall quietneſſe (which can onely make us happy in this world) nor endanger our everlaſting Peace, we are affraid to venture haſtily upon that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is of ſuch dangerous conſequence to erre, namely the binding our ſelves by Oath or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. We muſt deſire you to entertain this candid opinion of us, That we are no Oppoſers of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and their Authority, no Curious or Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Fault-finders, not wedded to ſingularity, or in love with our own brain-ſick Fancies; but ſuch as ſee and conſider how apt men are naturally to go aſtray, and do therefore endeavour to uſe all the helps that can be to guide us: We reſolve to lay aſide all ſelf-love, affection, prejudice, paſſion, and to look upon things, with as cleer, and impartiall eyes, as fleſh and blood may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, through divine aſſiſtance. We are very much grieved, that we ſhould be thought not to ſee that which others take to be as cleer as the light, when as yet we are willing to ſubmit to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49373:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>whatſoever ſhall be evidenced to us from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and right Reaſon; and ſhall be thankfull to any who ſhall be the happy inſtruments to reduce us from errour, (if ſo it be an errour with you, to be fearfull of plunging our ſelves into damnation) We therefore had acceſſe to you, when you undertook the explaining of the Scottiſh Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, (as it is called) yet (it ſo falls out) that in ſtead of ſatisfaction, we found more ſcruples from it, then before your explanation. We hear you are a Member of that grave Aſſembly, and ſo we thought you might be able to ſay as much as could be ſaid in defence thereof; but we muſt tell you, That in your diſcourſe, we obſerved ſome things fell from you contradictory to your own princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; ſome things in this Oath which occaſion the greateſt doubting you paſt by and diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled; ſometimes you made uſe of ſuch open Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacies, as the weakeſt Member of your Aſſembly would have thought ſcorn to have been puzled with: In a word, moſt you delivered, ſeemed ſo weak and groundleſſe, that the fruit of that dayes hearing might very well be onely this; to confirm us in an opinion of the unlawfulneſſe of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and in a reſolution of never taking it.</p>
            <p>The part of Scripture, which you made uſe of, for making way to your explanation of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. where is contained the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that <hi>Moſes</hi> in behalf of God, renews with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> after that which was formerly made in <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai,</hi> where they covenanted with God to receive his Laws and Statutes; There <hi>Moſes,</hi> to induce
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49373:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>them to it, makes a recapitulation of the great things that God had done for them; and (as you expreſſe it) ſpeaks unto them, as if ſome father ſhould ſpeak unto his ſon whom he is to binde as an Apprentice, after ſome time of tryall had of his Maſter; <hi>Loe, you have had tryall of your ſervice, and the goodneſſe of your maſter thus long, ever ſince you came out of the land of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and will ye now indent with him to ſerve him, and to be his people?</hi> you applied it to us of this Land, in this or the like manner; <hi>We have had tryall of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, above theſe fourſcore yeers, ever ſince the time of Reformation;</hi> And then you extoll the goodneſſe of God to this Land, and that deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly; <hi>Never people enjoyed ſuch favours as we have done; great mercies, great deliverances, as any Nation under Heaven?</hi> Good Sir, we are glad to hear there was ever any Reformation amongſt us: we had thought we had been ſtill in <hi>Egypt,</hi> under the bondage of the man of Perdition, when we hear the reputed Zealous men of this age cry out of our <hi>Doctrine, Diſcipline, Government, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie,</hi> as <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian.</hi> It's rare, (we muſt confeſſe) to meet with ſo much ingenuity in the Sermons of moſt that go your way. Well, it is confeſſed by you, There is a Reformation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and ſuch a one as hath been counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced with many excellent favours from above, (ſuch as are, <hi>deliverances from imminent dangers, from open violence, and ſecret treachery of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of our Religion; ſetled Peace and tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the renown of this Nation farre and neer,)</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:49373:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>which have made us a glorious Church, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in Chriſtendome: (For though afterwards in your diſcourſe you took occaſion to cry down thoſe that cry up this Church for a glorious Church, yet you had little reaſon for it, ſo long as you confeſſe this Church to have been ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by Almighty God with extraordinary fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, which are as precious ornaments, and adde an outward luſtre to her inward beauty and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and ſo make her glorious:) then it is ſtrange we ſhould be ſo extreamly weary of this preſent Government, under which we have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed ſuch mercies: The benefits that have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied it might ſtill be encouragements to us to ſubmit unto it, eſpecially when (as wiſe men know well enough) alterations in Publique mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are ſo dangerous: for, ſuppoſe there were ſomething in our Government or Diſcipline to be reformed, (as in the beſt ordered Politie that can be, ſomething, upon good reaſon eſtabliſhed at firſt, may in time grow burthenſome and inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient:) yet are theſe of ſuch moment, as rather then bear them, you will engage the Kingdoms in a moſt deſperate War, and venture the ruining of Church and State, the deſolation of the Land, nay, the ſhaking of the very foundation of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, by means of ſuch Hereſies as grow apace in ſuch confuſed times as theſe. <hi>Calvin</hi> is ſearce of your minde, who (though diſ-affected to ſome of our Ceremonies and Liturgie, yet) is ſo moderate as to call them, <hi>toler abides ineptiae,</hi> trifles that might be born with, rather then cauſe a greater miſch of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49373:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Schiſme or Sedition. And certainly, for any to think that the reforming or removing theſe trifles (as he calls them) is able to countervail half the blood-ſhed, and other miſchiefs that are come upon us, is altogether unchriſtian and inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane too, and ſavours of an heart, that hath yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſelf to be ruled by the ſpirit of perverſneſſe and diſobedience. The diſeaſe is far more tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to us, and leſſe diſpleaſing unto God, then ſuch a kinde of remedie. God bleſſe us from ſuch Phyſicians, whoſe mediernes put us into a far worſe condition then ever our maladies could.</p>
            <p>But not to infiſt long upon that where your ſelf made but a ſhort ſtay: After you had laid this part of Scripture before the people, (though indeed it makes nothing for you, yet you are ſo conſident as to alledge every place that mentions but the name of Covenans, as pleading for you) then you paſſe to a generall diviſion of this Covenant, into the Title and Contents. The Title, <hi>viz: A folemn League or Covenant;</hi> there you lay down the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Covenant, which you define thus, <hi>A bond, whereby any one bindes himſelf unto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, for the performance of ſomething mutually agreed upon by eath party.</hi> Here, by the way, we doubt whether each particular in this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantis agreed upon by both parties. He to whom we binde our ſelves, is God, and of his conſent, we have no other way to judge, but by his will revealed: and if we ſearch the whole Book of God, we ſhall not be able to finde any probability of his conſent, that we ſhould enter into a ſolemn
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49373:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>League for aboliſhing thoſe Laws, and that form of Government under which we live, without the conſent of Him that by Gods ſpeciall Ordinance is appointed our Soveraign Lord and King. Befides each point of this Covenant is not agreed upon amongſt your ſelves; For, how many be there, who are enjoyned to enter into this League, that know not what the Doctrine or Diſcipline of <hi>Scotland</hi> is, that they muſt defend; they hope, perchance, it's good, becauſe commended to them by men reputed wiſe &amp; underſt anding: but what raſhneſſe is it in the mean time, for men to ſubſcribe to that which they know not; &amp; therefore muſt needs doubt, whether it may be done or not. Nor are all agreed about the aboliſhing of Epiſcopacy. If not the greateſt, yet ſurely a great part of this Kingdom, are well opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nioned of that Office and know that the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of ſome above others in the Clergy, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the word of God, and the examples of the pareſt times; and that Prelacy is uſed very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juriouſly, when 'tis ranked amongſt thoſe ugly and hatefull names of <hi>Papery, Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſme, Prophaneneſſe,</hi> of purpoſe to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear alike evill, with thoſe whoſe company it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced to keep: and that, what is amiſſe therein, may with leſſe labour, and more advantage to the State, and Religion both be Reformed, then the whole Fabrich be taken down. Nor yet are all of thoſe who ſtand for the aboliſhing of Epiſcopacy, agreed about this <hi>[Reformation according to the word of God.]</hi> No queſtion but the Independants, when they take this Covenant, have another meaning
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49373:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>then the Preſbyterians have, thinking that their Diſcipline is onely warranted by the word of God; and then, what mutuall agreement is there, or what Conſent in the raking of this Covenant, amongſt thoſe ſeverall ſorts that take it; though the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivers of it have dealt ſo ſubtily, as to put it into ſuch generall terms, that there might be no bog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on ſtarting aſide, but that each ſort might take it, though intellding ſeverall ſenſes.</p>
            <p>After this definition you pinoced to the diviſion of a Covenant into <hi>Sacred, Civill</hi> &amp; <hi>Mixt;</hi> which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference the nature of the Subject puts upon them, as being <hi>Sacred</hi> onely, or <hi>Civill</hi> onely, or partly <hi>Sacred,</hi> and partly <hi>Civill.</hi> This preſent Covenant you call <hi>Sacred,</hi> though you have no warrant from the Title, that is ſet before it, (where tis onely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>[A Solemn League or Covenant:]</hi> nor yet from the matter or contents thereof. For the four laſt Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of this Covenant, containe things meerly Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, (as will eaſily appear to any indifferent judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.) And as for the other two, which concern Preſervation of Religion in <hi>Scotland</hi> and Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>England:</hi> Religion, we grant, is Sacred, but as for defending, preſerving, reſorming, they proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belong to the Civill Magiſtrate, and are effected by that power that God hath committed to him. So that we cannot perſwade our ſelves, that you ſhould think it to be agreeable to the truth, to call this a <hi>Sacred League,</hi> onely you perceive that otherwiſe it might be ſome diſadvantage to the cauſe. The name of <hi>Sacred</hi> ſets it out with greater credit, and makes it more readily to be embraced.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49373:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>But yet it is fit to be examined, whether or no, you and the reſt of the Confederacy, are not guilty of laying ſnares, &amp; ſcandals for your Brethrens Feet, when (that you may the ſooner draw them into this League) you perſwade them, It is no other but a <hi>Sacred Covenant,</hi> ſuch a one as <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and their Governours made with God, to receive his Laws, and to be his people; and ſuch a Vow as we make in Baptiſme to renounce the Devill, and the other Enemies of our Salvation, and to give up our ſelves in a conſtant, and ſincere obedience; When it is as cleer as the Sun, it is nothing elſe, but a League amongſt your ſelves, for ſtrengthning of your party for defending of that Cauſe they have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken: and the main ſcope and intention is the ſubverſion of the preſent eſtabliſhed government. And what need have we then, poor people, to look to our ſelves, when we have gotten ſuch pernicious guides? for however, we are now perſwaded, That this is nothing elſe but a <hi>Sacred Vow</hi> to reform and repent, and give up our ſelves to be Gods People: yet when as we ſhall have entred into this League, we ſhall be preſſed to thoſe actions, which we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend under the horrid ſhapes of Sedition, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, Unjuſtice, Sacriledge. We ſhall be urged then in a tumultuous way to root out Epiſcopacy, which we have heard to have continued in all Chriſtian Churches ſince the Apoſtles times, and bekeve it to be very good, if good men mannage it. And this muſt be done too, againſt the Authority of our Soveraign, by taking up Arms, which tend either to deſtroy him, or elſe to compell him to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49373:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſent; whom notwithſtanding, we have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſworn, that we do acknowledge Supream in all cauſes both Eccleſiaſticall and Temporall: If you dare ſpeak out Sir, you cannot but confeſſe this to be the chief intention of this <hi>Solemn League and Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From thence to the Anatomizing of the body of this Covenant, wherein you obſerve; firſt, the <hi>Preface,</hi> ſecondly, <hi>the Subſtance;</hi> thirdly, <hi>the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion:</hi> And in the Preface; firſt, the perſons Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting <hi>[We Noblemen, Barons, Knights, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Burgeſſes, Miniſters of the Goſpell, and Commons of all ſorts:]</hi> Great names indeed, and a goodly train to draw on more Company; yet we ſuppoſe here are but <hi>genera ſingulorum,</hi> not <hi>ſinguli generum;</hi> ſome of all ſorts; not all, by a great many. God be thanked there be ſome right Noble and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Spirits, that cannot, withall the dread of Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, be frighted from their Allegiance to their Prince, and care of diſcharging a good conſcience towards God: But will rather ſuffer the ſpoyling of their goods, and the loſſe of all that is dear unto them, then be induced to joyn in this Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. But yet we can ſpie no King amongſt this goodly train, and it ſeemes there is none indeed, by ſuch bold attempts as theſe are. And hence grows the neceſſity of this League: The <hi>quondam</hi> Subjects, having broke aſſunder the bond of their Allegiance, which tyes Subjects together amongſt themſelves, and all unto their Prince, hereupon they finde themſelves to be ſomewhat too looſe, and ſo ſeek to binde themſelves together again by
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49373:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>this mutuall League. Yet it is much that the King cannot be made to enter into League with theſe <hi>Noblemen, Barons, Knights,</hi> and <hi>Burgeſſes,</hi> againſt himſelf, as well as he is heretofore feigned to take up Arms with them againſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>But at laſt by chance the King comes in <hi>[living under one King]</hi> ſurely there was a fault in Printing; for the King is <hi>under. [And being of one Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion,]</hi> We wonder Sir, how all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Aſſembly can take this Covenant whileſt this Clauſe is in, or how all men in this great City ſhould, which for multiplicity of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions is become another <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing you faſten upon in the Preface is, the generall ends, which are four. The firſt is <hi>the glory of God,</hi> according to that of <hi>Luther; In nomine Domini, &amp;c. [having before our eyes the glory of God.]</hi> There be a great number now a dayes, who make fair pretences of having <hi>the glory of God</hi> before their eyes; when their actions wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt them, That they have not his fear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their eyes. It is an uſuall thing to ſee men row one way and look another: And as uſuall is that So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leciſme which the Stage-player once committed; who pointed to the earth, when he ſpake of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Was God ever more diſhonoured then now he is in his Word, Worſhip, Ordinances, in mens unchriſtian, if not inhumane Carriages towards one another. Well, the world may be blinded, but God is not mocked: He will have his glory from us in the end, without or beſide our intention. His Wiſdom knows how to turn the ſins of men,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49373:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>(and amongſt them their hypocriſie) to his glory. But in this, we onely condemn ſome mens acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; we judge no mans heart; let every one ſtand or fall to his own Maſter. The next is <hi>[the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Kingdom of Ieſus Chriſt]</hi> There is loud talking now of <hi>advancing the Kingdom of Ieſus Chriſt, and ſetting him upon his Throne;</hi> of purpoſe ſure to dazle the Peoples eyes, with theſe glorious Titles which are put upon this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Cauſe. <hi>The Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, is this; That Soveraignty, and rule that Chriſt by the power of his Word and Spirit doth exerciſe in the hearts and lives of Chriſtians, beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down thoſe ſinfull luſts that oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and enclining the hearts of men to Faith and to Obedience: ſo that when we give up our ſelves to be governed and ordered by his precepts, then we ſubmit to his Scepter, and advance his Kingdom. Now alas, how is his bleſſed example in the moſt part ſleighted? how unworthily are thoſe Pearls of his heavenly doctrine trampled under foot? It were an argument of Malignancy now to preſſe upon the Conſcience, thoſe rules of ſelf-denyall, of following Chriſt, of making Peace, of forgiving offences, &amp;c. It is too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mifeſt there be many deprived, ſome of liberty, ſome of livelihood, for no other crimes, that the world can charge them with, but, thus ſeeking to <hi>advance the Kingdom of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next comes in <hi>[The honour and happineſſe of the Kings Majeſty]</hi> witneſſe thoſe ſlanders we daily hear and read from Pulpits and Pamphlets, which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49373:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>tend to no other end, but to bring contempt and hatred upon that Sacred Majeſty, concerning whom we ought to make conſcience of our thoughts.</p>
            <p>The fourth, and laſt of theſe godly ends, is <hi>[The Publique liberty, ſafety and Peace of theſe Kingdoms.]</hi> What? by entring into a League, to engage the Kingdoms in a moſt deſperate War, and bringing in a forreign Nation to encreaſe our miſeries? A pretty riddle; to preſerve the Liberties and Peace of the Kingdoms by deſtroying them.</p>
            <p>Next in order are the Motives or Inducements to this League; this the firſt, <hi>[Calling to minde the treacherous and bloody Plots, Conſpiracies, and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the enemies of God againſt the true Religion]</hi> What then? muſt we caſt out one Devill by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; nay, by caſting out one, poſſeſſe our ſelves of ſeven worſe? we ſay nothing in defence of this ſort of men: we abhor their councells; and ſay as old <hi>Iacob</hi> did concerning his two ſons, <note place="margin">Gen. 49.</note> 
               <hi>My ſoul ſhall not come into their ſecret place, nor be joyned with their aſſemblies:</hi> Their wrath is fierce, their rage is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, their poyſon is rank and deadly, they are ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies enough and they bear a tyrannous hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſtour Church; but we could wiſh there were not other troublers of Iſrael beſides them; ſuch as are among us, but are not of us; that oppoſe <hi>Rome,</hi> and yet uphold her; that by their attempts and practiſes, excuſe the practiſes of the Romiſh Synagogue; and (as if ſhe were not impudent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough already) adde more braſſe to the forehead of that Whore of <hi>Balylon.</hi> We wonder Sir, what
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49373:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Proteſtant Partie ſhall be able hereafter to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Popes Factors, the Jeſuits, for their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Plots, for deſtroying Kings, undermining States, raiſing Sedition, exempting Subjects from their obedience, when as our preſent proceedings in that kinde, may juſtly ſtop our mouthes, and make us bluſh with ſhame, as having equalled, if not in ſome ſort exceeded them. You ſay, What you do now is for Religion and the Gauſe of Chriſt: and they as much, That what they attempt is for Religion and the Catholique Cauſe, and ſo the iſſue of the controverſie will be the ſame.</p>
            <p>Another motive is, <hi>[The deplorable eſtate of</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>the diſtreſſed eſtate of</hi> England, <hi>and the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous eſtate of</hi> Scotland] For <hi>Scotland,</hi> we know not, nor hear of any dangers attending them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Fears and Jealouſies, which being hanſomely managed, by the politique contrivers of this War, may draw ſuch dangerous conſequents upon them as ours have done upon us. For <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> their condition is ſad and lamentable, and the courſe that is now taken is no means at all of curing them, but of making their wounds more deep and gaſtly.</p>
            <p>A third motive is, <hi>[The failing of other means, Supplications, Remonſtrances, Proteſtations,]</hi> And yet what one thing was ever denyed by His Majeſty which was fitting for a King to give away, or for Subjects to require. All the ſecurity for Religion and Liberty that could conveniently be made, was fairly offered.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt motive is <hi>[The practice of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49373:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe Kingdoms in former times, and the example of Gods people in other Nations:]</hi> It's marvell you gave no inſtance in your Explanation; it will be hard to finde one in all our Hiſtories, that may be a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident for ſuch a Covenanting as this: we have heard of none more like it, then that League of Aſſociation, which the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> made for ſtrengthning of themſelves againſt oppoſition; which they had cauſe to fear: or that <hi>la ſainte Ligue,</hi> the holy League, of late yeers in <hi>France;</hi> and ſure you will be aſhamed to make either of thoſe your pattern. But as for the example of Gods people in other Nations, you inſtance in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants that <hi>Moſes</hi> made; and <hi>Ioſhuah, Iehoida, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah, Nehemiah, &amp;c.</hi> Cuſtome of ſinning how im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent it makes men to be? ſtrange that you ſhould not be aſhamed at length, to make ſuch gulls of poor ſimple people, to delude them with ſuch no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious falſities, and ſo deceive them to their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; and as ſtrange that the people ſhould endure any longer to be thus perniciouſly abuſed: Let any man but of the meaneſt underſtanding, ſearch where theſe Covenants are regiſtred, and compate any of them with this;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.12. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.</note> he ſhall eaſily perceive a vaſt difference, both for the manner, and the matter. In thoſe Jewiſh Covenants, we finde the whole Nation Covenanting, and not ſome particular Faction: The Prince or ſupream Magiſtrate (as <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua</hi> were) conſent and call the people to their Covenant: not ſome of the People bandye themſelves together againſt their Prince, and others of their fellow-Subjects: In
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49373:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe Jewiſh Covenants, the matter was ſo appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly juſt and good, that none could queſtion it: The matter of this Covenant ſeems ſo unjuſt to many, and is of it ſelf ſo dubious and ſuſpicious, that moſt men muſt be preſſed and urged to it, and threatned for refuſall, when indeed a Vow or Covenant ſhould be voluntary. To conclude, (as it may be collected from thoſe places) this is the ſum and ſubſtance of the Covenants the Jewes made with God; <hi>viz: To be the Lords people; to have nothing to do with Baal; to abhor the Idolatry of the Nations; to walk after the Lord, and to keep his Statutes, and his Iudgements, with all their heart, &amp;c.</hi> If this were the ſubſtance of this Covenant now enjoyned, he were not worthy to live upon the earth that would refuſe it.</p>
            <p>It appears therefore ſufficiently to every conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering man, how little reaſon there is from any of theſe motives to induce us to enter into this League or Covenant.</p>
            <p>So from the Preface to that which you call the ſubſtance of this Covenant. The firſt branch of the firſt Article whereof is this; <hi>[we ſhall endeavour in our ſeverall places, the preſervation of Religion in the Church of</hi> Scotland, <hi>in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and Government]</hi> This you ſaid was no more then deſiring the good of Gods Church, according to that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 122.7, 8. And if that be all, may they long enjoy it; we ſhall pray for the peace of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem in generall, in ſpeciall for them, they are our Brethren and Neighbours; we wiſh them
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49373:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>proſperity, and ſhall ſeek to procure their welfare. But we would fain be reſolved of this: Whether or no, when we vow the preſervation of Religion in the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> as it is now eſtabliſhed for Diſcipline and Governmens, we do not binde our ſelves by Oath, to preſerve unalterably that which is alterable of it ſelf; and may be altered upon occaſion, if the neceſſity of the Church re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires? ſeeing it is held by all the ſoundeſt and moſt learned, That forms of Diſcipline and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, may be altered at leaſt in many things that appertain unto them; and we finde by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience daily that ſome Lawes and Orders which were good at firſt, afterwards do grow inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient.</p>
            <p>The next branch in that firſt Article is, [<hi>The Reformation of Religion in</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland] In our Proteſtation, we vowed to maintain &amp; defend the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> now we ſwear to reform that Doctrine; ſurely this is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what prepoſterous: firſt, we ſhould have reformed it, &amp; then after we knew what it was, maintain and defend it. This, for ought we ſee, is no better then the taking of Gods name in vain. 1, we ſwear to maintain the true reformed Proteſtant Religion; which might well ſeem a ſtrange expreſſion: we uſed to know is by the name of <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> which doth implie, <hi>Reformed;</hi> but it ſeems it is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> till it be again <hi>Reformed;</hi> and then it muſt be <hi>truly Reformed,</hi> before it can come to the power and purity. Then we muſt ſwear to reform it, though which way it muſt be done, or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49373:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>how far this reformation muſt proceed, we know not: Then if this Reformation pleaſe not uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant heads, there muſt be another <hi>League for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation;</hi> This is plainly to ſwear to we know not, or care not what.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[The Reformation of Religion in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government]</hi> Here's all out of frame it ſeems, nothing right; yet there is nothing in the Doctrine of our Church expreſſed in the 39. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and Homilies, but all conſonant to the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Confeſſions of other Churches: The greateſt Corruption in Doctrine that is amongſt us, is in that point of Obedience to the Prince, as they ſhall finde, who read the <hi>Homilies againſt Rebellion and Diſobedience.</hi> And for Diſcipline and Government, what is amiſſe therein hath ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceeded from the fault of theſe that exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe it, then from the Diſcipline it ſelf.</p>
            <p>But you cry out and ſay, <hi>[It muſt be no longer diſſembled; A great many things there are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; A great deal of Superſtition to be caſt out; Defects in the Liturgy &amp; in the Government.]</hi> Sir, it is not fair to bring a generall Defamation, when you have no ſpeciall charge. We wonder you have ſate thus long, and framed no Articles of impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Liturgy, that the world may ſee how true this Accuſationis. But the Liturgy is uſed juſt as the Miniſters are; accuſed, ſilenced, ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, yet never called, nor heard to ſpeak in their own defence. Certainly this could not but be (we know not, whether advantagious to the Cauſe or not) yet a means of more ſatisfaction to the minds
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49373:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>of men, if you had expreſſed, what particulars you except againſt in our Diſcipline and Worſhip. For though we daily hear our Liturgy cryed down as <hi>Popiſh;</hi> our Ceremonies, as <hi>Superſtitious, raggs of Antichriſt,</hi> &amp;c. yet it is by ſuch as we have little cauſe to reſigne our underſtandings to, unleſſe we could ſee their mindes more calm from paſſion. For while we behold them boyling to ſuch uncharitableneſſe, their diſcourſe muſt needs be frothy, and their brains as empty of ſound judgement, as their tongues are full of bitterneſſe. We cannot but think them to be led with a blinde zeal, when they call light, darkneſſe; and know not to diſtinguiſh betwixt gold and droſſe. The Letany, they ſay, is conjuring, becauſe we pray to be heard <hi>by Chriſts Nativity and Circumciſion, by his precious death, &amp;c.</hi> a childiſh cavill: and <hi>the Buriall, Popiſh; becauſe there is no Scripture from one end to the other, that prayers were ſaid at Burials.</hi> It may be your ſelf is convinced, with ſome ſuch powerfull argument (for we hear you neglect the form appointed,) which if it be ſo, we may well be affraid to entruſt the reforming of our Religion into ſuch weak hands, though you are vouchſafed the titles of <hi>Godly</hi> and <hi>Learned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[According to the examples of the beſt reformed Churches]</hi> And who ſhall judge which are the beſt reformed? what hinders that this Church ſhould not be as well reformed as any, unleſſe becauſe it ſeems not to be ſo far removed from ſome Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies uſed in Popery: we know that vertue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts not in the furtheſt diſtance from one extream,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49373:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>but in a prudent mediocrity between both; ſo that Church is beſt reformed, that keeps a diſtance in her Worſhip, as well from Irreverence and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneſſe, as Superſtition. The wiſe Reformers of this Church had an eye to this; It was their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall care to abandon Popiſh Superſtitions; yet ſo as by decent orders eſtabliſhed, to procure a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verent reſpect unto Gods ſervice.</p>
            <p>The laſt branch of this Article is, <hi>[To endeavour to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdoms to the neereſt conjunction and uniformity of Religion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of Faith form of Church-government, &amp;c. That we and our poſterity, may as brethren, live together in Faith and Love]</hi> We are glad to hear any thing of <hi>Love,</hi> which is grown ſo much a ſtranger, that we had thought the very name of it had been quite buried in forgetfulneſſe. God onely is he that can unmask the heart, if men diſſemble; But let the world judge how little you ſeek this in earneſt, when you have blown up ſuch ſparks of diſſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; as have ſet theſe Kingdoms in a combuſtion, and rent in pieces Cities, Villages, Families; and are theſe the works of thoſe that endeavour to <hi>live in love?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Sir, is it not poſſible to retain Chriſtian love and unity, in the difference of Rites and Cuſtoms, and outward accidentall forms of Worſhip and Government?
<note place="margin">Calvin. reſponſ. ad Verſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellem Mediat.</note> Did not the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern Churches</hi> retain Communion, notwithſtanding the Difference about obſerving <hi>Lent</hi> and <hi>Eaſter?</hi> Hear him whoſe judgement we doubt not, you much approve, and that is Maſter <hi>Calvin. As concerning
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49373:13"/>rites in particular,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin: Ep: ad Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſula:</note> (ſaith he) <hi>let the ſentence of</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine <hi>take place, who leaves it free unto all Churches to retain their own Cuſtomes: yea ſometimes it profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and is expedient, that there ſhould be a difference, leſt men ſhould think that Religion it tyed to outward Ceremonies. [Poſſble,</hi> therefore, perchance, you will grant it is; but not ſo <hi>eaſie:]</hi> Well then, it will the more commend our Chriſtian diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that we can retain true brotherly love, where it is hard to be retained. To conclude, we won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how thoſe men dare ſpeak of <hi>Love,</hi> who have raiſed and fomented the moſt unnaturall diviſion that ever was: or how their hearts can be affected at all with Chriſtian Charity, who think the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhing or changing of thoſe things they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for in this Reformation, worth ſo much Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian blood-ſhed, beſides the ruining of the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Kingdom, and endangering the very ſubſtance of Religion.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Article <hi>[That we ſhall in like manner endeavour the extirpation of Popery]</hi> The moſt war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable courſe that could be taken for this end, the Kings Majeſty, (to whom this care belongs in chief) was pleaſed, long ſince, to commend to the two Houſes; that is, That the Children of Papiſts might be brought up in the Proteſtant Religion; and why was it not then accepted? But if this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation muſt be by murthering or baniſhing all of that Religion, depriving them of their Eſtates and goods, in which by the law of God and man they have Propriety, we doubt whether it may be done without manifeſt breach of the ſixth and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49373:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>eighth Commandements. Now we muſt ſwear, That we will extirpate them; yet the manner how it muſt be done is not expreſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Prelacy,</hi> that is, <hi>Church-Government by Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Deans and Chapters, &amp;c.]</hi> Here <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy</hi> is ſet between <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Superſtition,</hi> and ſo it is handled in that unworthy manner, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was by the ſpitefull Jews, when he was Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified between two Theeves, that ſo he might be thought as notorious a Malefactour, as thoſe were with whom he ſuffered. Now this queſtion may well ariſe from hence; How thoſe men (your ſelf, as we ſuppoſe, and others) who have taken Sacred Orders, ſhall be diſpenſed withall for their Oathes of Obedience to their ſpirituall Governours, and their ſeverall ſubſcriptions to the preſent eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed government, (which implyed an approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:) unleſſe to pull down <hi>Prelacy,</hi> you care not to uphold <hi>Popery,</hi> by diſpenſation of Oathes; as ſome of no ſmall account amongſt you did in the caſe of the Souldiers taken by the King at <hi>Braince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, you muſt needs grant, That the Oath of Canonicall Obedience, bindes, ſo long as <hi>Prelacy</hi> ſtands; and <hi>Prelacy</hi> ſtands after this League or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant taken: notwithſtanding ſo many <hi>Barons, Knights, and Burgeſſes</hi> have vowed the extirpation of it, (for when they vow the extirpation of it; that doth imply It is not yet extirpate, nor abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed;) Well then, ſuppoſe this, (which may very well be ſuppoſed) that your Dioceſan, or Biſhop, ſhall command you by all means you lawfully
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49373:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>may, to countenance Epiſcopall Government, and to uphold it; and in your Sermons, (as occaſion ſhall be, to ſhew how agreeable it is to the word of God, and to the firſt and pureſt times; if you obey him not, you are forſworn, by reaſon of that Oath you made to obey him and his Succeſſours, in their lawfull and juſt Commands: and on the other ſide, if you do obey him, you are forſworn too, by taking this new League and Covenant, wherein you have vowed the extirpation of Epiſcopacy. It will trouble you Sir, to winde your ſelf out of this <hi>Dilemma.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe ſhame will not ſuffer you to declaim with ſuch violence and bitterneſſe (as ſome of your Brethren do;) againſt that which formerly you have approved; you told us, in your Explanation, you would ſay no more of this Government, then was the cenſure of the Parliament in that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of theirs for <hi>calling an Aſſembly of Learned and Godly Divines:</hi> And there is a four-fold Charge againſt Epiſcopacy, (yet God forbid that all the Charges there drawn up ſhould be true:) Firſt, <hi>that it is evill,</hi> But whether <hi>in ſe,</hi> or <hi>in effectu,</hi> you will not diſpute, you told us: We will excuſe you, Sir; We perceive you were not made for diſputing, that have learned to diſtinguiſh no better. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is evill in it ſelf, muſt needs be ſo in the effects; <hi>For an evill Tree cannot bring forth good fruits,</hi> you know who ſaid it. And whatſoever is evill in the effects, is ſo in it ſelf alſo, by that known <hi>Maxime: Quod efficit tale eſt magis tale.</hi> So that if Prelacy be evill one way, it muſt as neceſſarily be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49373:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo the other. And if it be not evill <hi>in ſe,</hi> it is not at all evill; and ſo you may well ſave the labour of diſputing, the queſtion falls. But to prove it evill, ſome way or other, you added this <hi>[Certainly, if it were good, ſo many godly Miniſters had not ſuffered under it]</hi> To anſwer that; Firſt, it is well enough known, That when the Diſcipline of the Church, or Laws of this Land (though not to the height of ſeverity) have been executed againſt thoſe, whoſe tongues are the trumpets of Sedition; it hath been their cuſtome to cry out of Cruelty and Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and in the mean time to perſecute worſe with the ſting of their tongue or pen, thoſe whom they conceived were the authors or occaſioners of their puniſhment, though deſerved moſt juſtly, by their breach of Order and Chriſtian Unity. And the miſerable confuſion of theſe times doth ſhew ſufficiently, how dangerous it would have proved to the State to have paſſed by ſuch Incendiaries, with connivence, and indulgence.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuppoſe that ſome men in the <hi>Prelacy,</hi> have unjuſtly vexed ſome <hi>Godly Miniſters;</hi> yet a Member of the Aſſembly (as you are) may (we hope) have ſo much skill, as to diſtinguiſh the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the Office: and not to ſlander the calling with the imputation of that, which is the fault of thoſe that bear it. But it hath been obſerved long ſince, that amongſt other devices you have to make this worthy calling others you uſe to rip up the faults of Governours, with exceeding ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; nay, you impute all the faults and miſchmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours abounding in the world, unto this form of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49373:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>Eccleſiaſticall Government, under which we live: when as indeed theſe faults ariſe from humane frailty, and the common depravation of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and have been and will be alwayes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of more or leſſe, what form of Government ſoever ſhall take place. And you may, with the like ſhew of reaſon, impute thoſe errours and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions which we finde reproved by the Prophets in the common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> unto that form of Jewiſh Government of which you cannot deny, God him ſelf was authour, as you may charge the Office of Epiſcopacy with thoſe miſdemeanours and abuſes that are found among us.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, It is charged by that Ordinance <hi>[to be offenſive and burthenſome:]</hi> We verily think it is, to thoſe whoſe haughty mindes diſdain to ſee any above themſelves, and whoſe ſtiffe necks can hardly endure to be yoked with any, though the eaſieſt kinde of Subjection and Obedience. To ſuch Monarchy it ſelf is burthenſome; And if (to ſatisfie their deſires) they ſhould be ſuffered to caſt off that, any other Government would quickly be as burthenſome.</p>
            <p>Thirdly <hi>[it is an hinderance to Reformation</hi> ſaith that Ordinance &amp; ſo ſay you:] No marvell indeed, if <hi>Reformation</hi> be to extirpate Epiſcopacy: What? you ſeek to root out the Biſhops; and the Biſhops ſeek what they can to uphold and maintain their calling. This the Law of ſelf-preſervation teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that <hi>Supream Law,</hi> that teacheth you alſo, now to take up Arms againſt the King.</p>
            <p>Fourthly it is charged, <hi>[to be prejudiciall to the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49373:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>State and Government of this Kingdom.]</hi> As wiſe a man as any Member of either Houſe thought otherwiſe when he ſaid, <hi>No Biſhop, no King.</hi> But how is it prejudiciall? You endevour to ſhew us, in your Explanation. <hi>[The ſtate of this Kingdom</hi> (ſay you) <hi>is Parliamentary, and the Parliament and Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy are not well conſorted; there is Antipathy between them]</hi> Now you have confeſſed the truth by chance, that <hi>the world may bear witneſſe of your loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: that you have no thoughts to diminiſh His Majeſties juſt Power and Greatneſſe:</hi> No, by no means, though you exclude him, from bearing the chiefeſt part in Government. The government of this Kingdom, you tell us is <hi>Parliamentary,</hi> with which <hi>Prelacy</hi> is not well conſorted. So that the Biſhops muſt needs be caſt out for their <hi>Antipathy.</hi> Let the King look to himſelf; his turn will be the next. But to end our Anſwer to this Charge; Let this worthy Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice be laden with all the ſlanders that envie can caſt upon it; let it be charged as deeply as the Earl of <hi>Strafford,</hi> or the Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury;</hi> yet, you cannot be ignorant, That the Antiprelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call partie, (which you ſide with) hath been often challenged to ſhew any Church ſince the time that the bleſſed Apoſtles were converſant upon earth, that hath been ordered by any other but Epiſcopall Government, beſides ſome in theſe laſt times, which for inſolency, pride, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of all good order, are found to be the worſt: and they never yet were able to do it; nor ever will be.</p>
            <p>In the next place is <hi>[Superſtition]</hi> That is, (as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49373:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>you ſay) <hi>whatſoever it uſed in Gods worſhip, without expreſſe warrant from the word.</hi> This deſcription is ſo large, that a Gown or Surplice, a Rayle about a Table, a geſture of kneeling, or ſtanding up, &amp;c. will come within the circumference of it: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed moſt of you, in your popular Sermons uſe to bring each of theſe under the laſh of <hi>Superſtion.</hi> It had been right, if you had ſaid; That whatfore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is brought into the Church of God, and held as a neceſſary part of his Worſhip, without warrant from the Word, that is <hi>Superſtition:</hi> So that's a ſuperſtitious opinion which is hold by many of your partie, when they make one geſture effentiall and neceſſary to the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, namely, Sitting, and condemn the other of Kneeling to be Idolatrous.</p>
            <p>Next to Superſitition, is <hi>[Haereſie, Schiſme, &amp;c]</hi> Here you inſtance in <hi>Socinianiſme, Arminianiſme, Antinoinianiſme, Anabaptiſme.</hi> There be ſome too, (as we hear) in the holy Aſſembly, that deny the Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt from the Father and the Son; What call ye them? muſt they paſſe for <hi>Orthodox?</hi> But you gave no inſtance for <hi>Schiſme;</hi> yet never more plenty; never was the bond of Communion of Saints, broken into ſo many pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe of a Rite or Ceremony; when as yet we all agree in one Faith, have received one Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, acknowledge and worſhip one God and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour. Oh Sir, <hi>Schiſine,</hi> was too near you to diſcern it well. If you know what <hi>Schiſme</hi> is; namely, the breach of Chriſtian Unity, and had but looked wiſhly upon your ſelf, you would have condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49373:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>your ſelf. Who can be more guilty of <hi>Schiſme</hi> then your ſelf and your Partie is. You make and take a Covenant here, which tends to make a new <hi>Schiſme</hi> in the Church and State, at leaſt to make the old one wider; and yet colour it over with a pretence of ſwearing againſt <hi>Schiſme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is therefore worth the noting, how well this Covenant is kept by thoſe that have power to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate theſe evils that grow upon us; To inſtance but in the <hi>Antinomians,</hi> It is well known there be many that Preach that Doctrine, and their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories frequented with multitudes of followers, yet where is the endeavour of extirpation, or any reſtraint at all? where is any <hi>ſtopping of the mouthes of ſuch as ſpeak things they ought not?</hi> No, when we urge this; we are told, <hi>The time is not yet &amp; they ſerve for the preſent to advantage the Cauſe, and promote the great deſigne in hand, &amp; therefore muſt be born with.</hi> But what a wicked policy is it in the mean time, for any end whatſover, to ſuffer ſo many ſouls to be poyſoned with erroneous Doctrine, when there is power to hinder it. Thus where there is little Conſcience made of taking Oathes, there will be as little of keeping them: Or it may be thoſe who have learned to diſpenſe with Oathes, have alſo got that other Jeſuiticall trick, of equivocating; and ſo they reſerve, when they take this Covenant, that it ſhall not binde them, <hi>ad ſemper,</hi> to endevour the extirpation of <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſme;</hi> but onely <hi>proſtaturerum,</hi> when it ſhall be no longer advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and ſerviceable for their ends.</p>
            <p>Now we come to the third Article, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49373:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>three things. Firſt <hi>[To endevour to preſerve the Rights and Priviledges of Parliaments:]</hi> They are like to be preſerved and defended well enough, by thoſe that know them better then we do; when they make it their priviledge, daily to command our Eſtates and Lives. Next, <hi>[The liberties of the Ringdoms:]</hi> And that will be an hard matter for us to do, <hi>viz.</hi> to preſerve our liberties, when we ſhall have ſworn to enſlave our Eſtates and Lives to the arbitrary diſpoſall of our fellow-Subjects. Then, becauſe he is <hi>Minor univerſis,</hi> in the laſt place comes in <hi>[the Kings perſon and Authority, which muſt be preſerved and defended in the preſervation and defence of the true Religion, and Liberties of the Kingdoms,]</hi> and no further, we ſuppoſe you mean it, though you are loath to ſpeak it out. For if ſo be he ſtands not <hi>in defence of Religion and Liberties;</hi> or if you conceive he doth not, then your generall tenent is, That he may be reſiſted, and you confirm it by your practice. God bleſſe His Majeſty, and ſend him a ſafer Guard, then you have been, or are like to be; you have endevoured all you can to bring his Perſon and Authority too, into a dangerous Eſtate. And ſurely, if he, <hi>by whom Kings Reign,</hi> and who will undoubtedly maintain thoſe, whom he hath made his Deputies, had not been his ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Guardian, he had been long before this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</p>
            <p>It follows, <hi>[That the world may bear witneſſe of our Loyalty:]</hi> The world ſees, and good mens hearts lament, the little Conſcience that is left of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> when they hear His Sacred Majeſty,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49373:17"/>reviled daily and made contemptible to the people, both in jeſt and earneſt, by Pamphlets and Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Certainly they that know but in groſſe what belongs to Royall Majeſty, cannot but ſee the Kings juſt Power and Greatneſſe by this time much diminiſhed. Is not the power of Arms, with which the Law hath entruſted him taken from him? and ſo he is diſabled of doing that, which his Office doth chiefly call him to, that is, to protect and defend his Subjects; ſo that in this one particular, you will ſcarcely be able to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your Loyalty, unleſſe holpen out with ſome of thoſe, (or ſuch like) diſtinctions, which neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath taught this age to make uſe of, to defend Rebellion. So you can defend his Authority and yet deſtroy his Perſon; reſiſt him as a man, not as a King, ye can do that and more too; you can defend Religion by courſes utterly condemned in that Religion.</p>
            <p>The fourth Article, <hi>[To endeavour the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of Incendiaries, Malignants, and evill Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, &amp;c.]</hi> And who are they <hi>[ſuch as divide the King from his people:]</hi> And ſuch too, as divide the People from their King. Such as <hi>Sheba</hi> and <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> were in Iſrael. Now who are in more eſteem with the City and Parliament, then thoſe who have been the chiefeſt Incendiaries of this War. Strange it is, that thoſe who ſound Alarms as far as <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſeek to engage this Kingdom more deſperately in this unnaturall War, ſhould be judged <hi>good Inſtruments and Well affected,</hi> and thoſe that Pray and Preach, and endeavour by all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49373:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>good means for Peace at home, ſhould be counted <hi>Incendiaries, and Malignants?</hi> It is our chief com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that there is a time to come, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be manifeſt, when every one ſhall receive according to his works. Before that time the Peace-makers muſt not look for their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed bleſſing.</p>
            <p>The fifth Article, concerns <hi>[The endeavouring that the Kingdoms may remain conjoyned in a firm Peace and Vnion to all Poſterity]</hi> God grant they may: but yet the <hi>Scots</hi> invading this Land with an Army, is thought by the wiſeſt to be contrary to the Articles of Pacification; and ſo no likely means to preſerve the Union of theſe Nations firm.</p>
            <p>The ſixth Article, concerns, 1. <hi>[The aſsiſting and defending all thoſe that ſhall enter into this League or Covenant, in what they ſhall do for the maintaining and purſuing thereof:]</hi> This might a great deal more eaſily have been ſwallowed, with ſuch a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation, as was once or twice uſed in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation; that is, <hi>[ſo for at lawfully I may]</hi> and <hi>ſo for as they ſhall lawfully purſue this Covenant.</hi> But it ſeems that any way of other mens purſuance of this League, and any way of our defending them in this purſuance, will be accounted lawfull.</p>
            <p>Then two things are ſpecified, againſt which we are to Covenant. Firſt, <hi>[Defection to the contrary part:]</hi> Apoſtacie indeed from the truth, and a good Cauſe; when we have once given our hands, is very wicked. And this Cauſe is evermore in your dicourſe, taken for granted, to be ſuch; The
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49373:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Cauſe of Religion, and a Cauſe that ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the glory of God. But how if your attempts and practiſes appear unto us to be againſt Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, againſt Allegiance to our Soveraign, againſt evident commands of Scripture, then this Cauſe muſt needs be a diſhonour unto God; and ſo to perſiſt in this League or Covenant, againſt the Conviction of our Conſciences, would be a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſigne and ſymptome of an heart given up to a reprobate ſenſe. But if you would have men to be ſo conſtant and reſolute in what they have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken, you ſhould take care before hand to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them well in theſe doubtfull caſes, and not ſuffer them to meddle with ſuch ſerious matters as Oaths and Covenants are, but upon <hi>mature deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration,</hi> and well grounded judgement, which all that enter into this Covenant, profeſſe they do, though moſt of them, perceive not ſo much as the generall ſcope thereof: beſides they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied in ſome points, and finde reluctancy in themſelves; yet are drawn into it, either by example, or elſe by terrours. And is there like to be conſtancy in ſuch mindes as theſe? you fear therefore, that ſome who have taken this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant at all adventures, ſhould afterwards chance to ſee ſome miſchief in it, which formerly their haſt would not let them ſee, and therefore you adde this as another cord to hold them faſt unto you for ever ſlipping back.</p>
            <p>The other thing againſt which we muſt Vow, is <hi>[Deteſtable Indiffirevey, or Neutrality in this Cauſe which ſo much concerns the glory of God, &amp;c.]</hi> There
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49373:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>you bring in that of our Saviour, <hi>He that is not with me, is againſt me.</hi> But ſtill you make uſe of that old Fallacy to enſnare us; you begge the queſtion, taking that for granted, which is ſtill in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, <hi>viz. That this Cauſe is Chriſts, and thoſe with him, who ſtand for you, and thoſe againſt him that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you.</hi> And thoſe who are not ſtrongly affected, to, and violent promoters of this Cauſe, you reckon amongſt Neuters and luke warm <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> who are neither hot nor cold. True it is, lukewarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in Religion is odious to Almighty God, who accepts no ſervice, but what comes from the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity and fervency of our love. He cannot endure the heart that is divided, that halts between two opinions, and that ſerves two Maſters. But Sir, you Comment beſides theſe Texts, when you make the not joyning our ſelves with you, and the ſlackneſſe in promoting your deſignes, to be this <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable Neutrality, and Indifferency,</hi> ſo odious to God and man. For it is evident how you have ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned your ſelves by Faction, and making parties a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people; by countenancing all ſorts of Sectaries, and Schiſmaticks; by exploding thoſe that concur not in opinion with you, and expoſing them to the violence of the diſtempered, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging multitude; by raiſing Tumults, and foment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sedition, amongſt the unquiet people; beſides we ſee daily, how unchriſtian other of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings are, how unjuſt your deſires, how par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, and far from equity are your judgements: And can we then ſafely joyn our ſelves with you, when as we profeſſe our ſelves to be Chriſts fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49373:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſee evidently, that theſe waies you take, can never be warranted by thoſe precepts of life that our maſter Chriſt hath ſet us? Do not all men cry out of this as a moſt unnaturall War? Doth it not appear to common ſenſe, to be moſt unnaturall, for Brethren, and Chriſtians, of the ſame Kingdom, of the ſame Reformed Religion, to be ſet upon violence, murther, cruelty, and to thirſt for blood? And how can we then ſide with you, but we muſt needs partake of your ſins, &amp; adde to the fomenting of a moſt unnaturall war? And though that may be a forcible motive to a carnall minde, which you tell us afterwards: <hi>[If Neuters, we are abhorred on both ſides, and out of the Protection of both:]</hi> This will be ſleighted of a truly magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Chriſtian, who cares not to diſpleaſe all the world ſo he may pleaſe his Maker. So long as we are under the ſhelter of a good conſcience we have God our Protector, and then what though all the powers of earth, and hell ſhould bandy themſelves againſt us? If earthly powers cannot or will not protect us, it may ſuffice that we are under the Care and Providence of a mercifull and powerfull God.</p>
            <p>But we hear every day, in your language, to be heady, and violent, is to be zealouſly affected; and ſo to be peaceable, is to be Neuters. So that will prove <hi>Neutrality,</hi> which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> commends, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration;</hi> and that Wiſdom Saint <hi>Iames</hi> deſcribes, which is <hi>Peaceable, and Tractable,</hi> to be <hi>Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers</hi> will be <hi>Neutrality,</hi> and yet ſuch are on Chriſts ſide, for he promiſes them a bleſſing.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49373:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>When think you Sir, ſhould there be uſe of theſe precepts of Chriſt and his Apoſtles if not now? A wonder it is to us, that this ſhould be the cauſe of Chriſt, and yet thoſe that defend it have ſo little of the minde of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But to perſwade us to be conſtant and reſolute, you take occaſion in your diſcourſe to perſwade us, that yours is the right and juſt cauſe; and to prove it you argue thus <hi>[where there is godlineſſe, on that ſide is God and Chriſt; but on your ſide is all the godlineſſe, and therefore God is on your ſide; and ſo the Cauſe you defend is his:]</hi> To anſwer that; firſt, we are ſo charitable as to think, that many honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, and good meaning people, being ſeduced into errours, (as who is free, and eſpecially, where there be the ſincereſt hearts, there is moſt danger of ſeducement, unleſſe there be the ſounder judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) are drawn to ſide with you, by the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of ſome Preachers, or example of others, of whoſe integrity they are well perſwaded; we are not to judge the cauſe by thoſe that defend it, but rather, by the certain rule of the word of God; which (God knows) is the errour of many poor ſouls in this preſent difference; they look at the men firſt, and then judge the Cauſe to be ſuch as thoſe men that ſtand for it ſeem to be. He that ſhall read the Hiſtory of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> ſhall finde that they ſcarce were exceeded by any living; in that abundant humility, ſtrictneſſe, ſanctity, zeal, devotion, which appeared in them. Theſe were taken in the world as pledges of their harmleſſe meaning; and did rather procure them
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49373:20"/>pity, then provoice harſh uſage. The worſt that underſtanding men conceived of them at firſt, was onely this, <hi>Oh quàm honeſtâ voluntate miſeri errant,</hi> with how good a meaning do theſe poor ſouls do evill? yet afterwards what Vipers proved they both to Church and State? This may ſuffice to ſhew, that it is a falſe rule of judging a Cauſe by thoſe that ſtand for it; when as they may either deceive by hypocriſie, or elſe be deceived by weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, you ſeem to be too unjuſt and Phariſaicall, whilſt you arrogate all Godlineſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Partie. What think you of thoſe good men, that are ſome of them at this preſent with the King, ſome in priſon, ſome deprived of their goods and livelihood for making conſcience of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and diſloyalty, yet have alwayes been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted ſpotleſſe and unblameable, and are the ſame men ſtill that ever they were; and ſome of them are renowned in forraign countries for their learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and their piety.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, you look upon your ſelves with an over-partiall eye; when you can ſee nothing but godlineſſe and godly men on your ſide: what think you Sir of <hi>Prince Griffith,</hi> and Col. <hi>M.</hi> (two godly Members indeed) not to mention more; theſe two are known well enough by their brave exploits; otherwiſe we ſhould be tender of their credits. And for your Souldiers, that fight for this <hi>holy Cauſe;</hi> thoſe who have had experience of their carriage in places where they have been Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, do think they can ſcarce be exceeded by the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49373:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>moſt profane rabble in the Kingdom for drinking and ſwearing &amp;c. And for thoſe that Preach for the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> they moſt of them make <hi>a gain of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and ſo can eaſily put on <hi>a form of godlineſſe.</hi> In a word, is there any man that will comply ſo far, as to preach, or fight, or ſpeak for the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of your deſignes any way diſcountenanced or diſcouraged; let his impiety, profaneſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts of ſeverity be what they will?</p>
            <p>It follows in this ſixth Article, <hi>[I ſhall zealouſly &amp; conſtantly all the dayes of my life continue in this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and ſeek to promote it againſt all oppoſition:]</hi> It were to be wiſhed, that this <hi>Zeal</hi> were not ſo much talked of, unleſſe it were better underſtood. It is but a paſſion of the minde, and ſo of it ſelf, (as all paſſions are,) neither good nor evill. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is uſed in a bad ſenſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zelos pikros, bitter envying. Iam</hi> 3.14. <hi>Zeloi Envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. Gal.</hi> 5.20.</note> as often as in a good. If it be without Charity, it is but that which the Apoſtle calls <hi>(bitter envying)</hi> If without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but blinde zeal; and ſo apt to do much miſchief, howſoever able to do little good. If without diſcretion, it is but raſhneſſe, and headi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. It were much ſafer therefore to teach the people how to moderate their Paſſions, then to take care to ſtir them up. To perſwade them to be zealous, and not together to inſtruct them how to regulate their zeal, that it may be charitable, juſt, and orderly, is but to teach them to be violent, ſeditions, tumultuous, &amp;c. And when they are ſuch, do not many think themſelves to be moſt zealous? Did not <hi>Paul</hi> in the time of his ignorance think he breathed of the ſpirit, when he breathed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49373:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>out threatnings againſt the Church?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Art.</hi> 9.</note> Did not <hi>Iehu</hi> bragge of zeal, when his ambition led him forth to ſuch attempts, which God reckoned but as cruelty and injuſtice?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.4.</note> And is not moſt of the zeal of theſe times ſet on edge with deſire of revenge, pride, or covetouſneſſe: witneſſe that greedineſſe in the men of this generation, and that unjuſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing themſelves of the Eſtates, the Lands, and Livings, of thoſe whom they Maligne, yet call them Malignants? So when they ſtuffe their Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with Curſings and Bitterneſſe; are they not thought to breath <hi>Zeal,</hi> pure <hi>Zeal?</hi> when they ſlander the footſteps of Gods anoynted, load thoſe that conſent not in opinion with them, with thoſe hatefull names of <hi>Malignants, Popiſhly affected;</hi> expoſe them hereby to violence, ſpoylings, plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring; when they profane the places of Gods publike worſhip, tear in pieces the Service-books; do ſuch things as a Turke or Pagan would make conſcience of; are not theſe things accounted the bleſſed fruits of <hi>Zeal?</hi> There is ſo much of this <hi>Zeal</hi> already, as makes the jealouſie of God to burn againſt us; This <hi>Zeal</hi> may we juſtly rank in the number of thoſe ſins, for which we are to <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our ſelves to be truly humbled,</hi> in the latter part of this Covenant. But it may be feared, the moſt are ſo far from being humbled, that they account that which indeed is their ſhame, to be their glory. And therefore God may juſtly laſh us into bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter mindes, untill we ſee our ſelves there to be moſt guilty, where we think we are moſt juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:49373:22"/>
            <p>So, to draw to a Concluſion. The laſtis the beſt part of all this Covenant, and the moſt needfull, namely <hi>[To acknowledge our unfeigned deſire to be humbled for our own ſins, and the ſins of this Nation; and to endeavour a reall Reformation of our ſelves, &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers under our power and charge:]</hi> Here be certain Nationall ſins reckoned up, againſt the firſt table of the Law, <hi>[as that we have not, as we ought, valued the ineſtimable benefit of the Goſpell nor laboured for the Power and Purity of it, &amp;c.]</hi> But if we look over again, we ſhall finde other Nationall ſinnes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo amongſt us, againſt the ſecond Table: (if we take Nationall in Doctor <hi>Taytoms</hi> ſenſe,
<note place="margin">In his Book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Prelacy.</note> for <hi>ſinnes eſtabliſhed by a Law.)</hi> So Diſobedience of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to that Ordinance God hath ſet over them; of Children to their Parents; Servants to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; are not theſe by new unheard of Votes and Ordinances made lawfull? Is not Sacriledge, Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, Plundring, Blood-ſhed, ſpeaking and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſlanders eſtabliſhed by a Law? Theſe are Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall ſinns therefore, and ſuch too as have a loud cry in the eares of the Almighty, and lay ſuch a guilt upon this Land, that we cannot expect he ſhould ſettle theſe Churches in Peace, untill they be ſome way or other explated, either by our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, or his revenging.</p>
            <p>And as for the Prayer in the cloſe of all, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>[you beſeech God to bleſſe your endeavours with ſuch ſucceſſe, as may be ſafety to his people, and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to other Churches to do the like?]</hi> He that ſhall duly obſerve the paſſages of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on both ſides, ſince theſe broyles began,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49373:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>how it hath fared with the King beyond all expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation; to what ſtrength he grew upon the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, notwithſtanding all the endevours to alienate the hearts of his Subjects from him what Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries he hath gotten; what Towns he hath gained, reducing the Northern and Weſtern parts of this Kingdom unto their former obedience; and that when you had poſſeſſed your ſelves of his Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zines, and ſtrongeſt Towns and Forts, your ſelves, for them off part, have been defented, foyled, loſt what you held, put to great ſtreights for Men and Money, notwithſtanding a rich and populous City wholly at your devotion, will conclude cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, there is little encouragement for you to go on in your deſignes, much leſſe for other Churches to take example by you, and to enter into League, or Aſſociation, againſt thoſe powers God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted over them, and to joyn together in ſuch at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, which tend ſo much <hi>to the diſhonour of God, the Scandalizing of the Profeſſion of Ieſus Chriſt, and the ruine and overthrow of Chriſtian Kingdoms and Common-wealths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir you need not much wonder to ſee a writing come to your hand in this manner, conſidering the Violence and Tyranny under which we live; when it is almoſt Capitall to make any ſcruple or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection which may queſtion the Infallibility of that great Court, or be a means to retard their proceedings in the grand deſigne. And we could not ſo much confide in you, as to have recourſe unto you, and expreſſe our doubts by way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49373:23"/>when we hear of many that are ſo fiercely carried on in promoting of this Cauſe. That they have vowed to betray their neereſt friends, that ſhall but ſpeak to the prejudice of it. Beſides, we are come neer to that paſſe, that the Roman State was in <hi>Domitians</hi> time, when, (as <hi>Tacitus</hi> writes) <hi>ademptum eſſet per inquiſitiones loquendi audiendique, Commercium;</hi> two men cannot without ſuſpicion and danger talk together; nor dare one neighbour diſcloſe his doubts, and ask the advice and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of another. More then that, we have by this means taken a more exact view of the ſeverall branches of this Oath, together with your expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the ſame. If now you have any thing to return to theſe things, (which we much doubt) we ſhall expect your Anſwer in ſome publique man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that ſo the benefit may redound to more; and what you ſhall do in this kinde, we ſhall accept with all Candour, as it becometh Chriſtians, and</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friends.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49373:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E pleaſed to take notice, that before theſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations could with conveniency be convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the hands of that Divine of the Aſſembly, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Title, who by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining and preſſing of this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant gave occaſion to them, he was taken out of this life; yet (as Charity bindes us) we muſt hope that, before his departure hence he had ſpace, and grace to repent of his errours, and of this in ſpeciall, one of his laſt, though doubtleſſe, none of his leaſt commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. If theſe Animadverſions, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Covenant (ſuch as they are) may be a means to keep any (who are
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49373:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>yet free) from entring into a League ſo unlawfull, ſo unchriſtian: or to reduce any, who through weakneſſe have been drawn into it, that ſo they might ſee and forſake their errour, and not by obſtinate perſiſting adde another offence unto the former; He that collected them with that inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and now preſents them to the Publique view, will account ſo good effects an abundant requitall for his pains.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="covenant">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49373:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Solemn <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> for Reformation, and defence of Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WE Noblemen, Barons, Knights, Gentlemen, Citizens, Burgeſſes, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell, and Commons of all ſorts in the Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the Providence of God li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving under one King, and being of one Reformed Religion, having before our eyes the glory of God, and the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Kingdom of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Jeſus Chriſt, the honour and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Kings Majeſty and His Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and the true publique Liberty, Safety, and Peace of the Kingdoms, wherein every ones private condition is included; and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to minde the treacherous and bloody Plots, Conſpiracies, Attempts, and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Enemies of God, againſt the true Religion, and Profeſſours thereof in all places, eſpecially in theſe three Kingdoms ever ſince the Reformation of Religion,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49373:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>and how much their rage, power, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, are of late, and at this time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed and exerciſed; whereof the deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate of the Church and Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the diſtreſſed eſtate of the Church and Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and the danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous eſtate of the Church and Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> are preſent and publique Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies; We have now at laſt, (after other means of Supplication, Remonſtrance, Proteſtations, and Sufferings) for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of our ſelves and our Religion, from utter Ruine and deſtruction, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the commendable practice of theſe Kingdoms in former times, and the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Gods People in other Nations; after mature deliberation, reſolved and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to enter into a mutuall and ſolemn League and Covenant, wherein we all ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, and each one of us for himſelf, with our hands lifted up to the moſt high God, do ſwear:</p>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>That we ſhall ſincerely, really, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, through the Grace of God, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in our ſeverall places and callings, the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49373:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>preſervation of the Reformed Religion in the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in Doctrine, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, againſt our common Enemies, the Reformation of Religion in the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> in Doctrine, Worſhip, Diſcipline, and Government, according to the Word of God, and the Example of the beſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, And ſhall indeavour to bring the Churches of God in the three Kingdoms, to the neereſt conjunction and Uniformity in Religion, Confeſſion of Faith, Form of Church-government, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory for Worſhip and Catechizing; that we and our Poſterity after us, may, as Brethren, live in Faith and Love, and the Lord may delight to dwell in the middeſt of us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>That we ſhall in like manner, without reſpect of perſons, indeavour the Extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Popery, Prelacie, (that is, Church-Government by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops, their Chancellors and Commiſſaries, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Archdeacons, and all other Eccleſiaſticall Officers depending on
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49373:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>that Hierarchy) Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſme, Prophaneſſe, and whatſoever ſhall be found to be contrary to ſound Doctrine, and the power of Godlineſſe; leſt we par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take in other mens ſins, and thereby be in danger to receive of their plagues, and that the Lord may be one, and his Name one in the three Kingdoms.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>III</head>
               <p>We ſhall with the ſame ſincerity, reallity, and conſtancy, in our ſeverall Vocations, endeavour with our eſtates and lives, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to preſerve the Rights and Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Parliaments, and the Liberties of the Kingdoms, and to preſerve and defend the Kings Majeſties Perſon and Authority, in the preſervation and defence of the true Religion, and Liberties of the Kingdoms, that the world may bear witneſſe with our conſciences of our Loyalty, and that we have no thoughts or intentions to diminiſh His Majeſties juſt power and greatneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>We ſhall alſo with all faithfulneſſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the diſcovery of all ſuch as have been, or ſhall be Incendiaries, Malignants,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49373:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>or evill Inſtruments, by hindring the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion, dividing the King from his people, or one of the Kingdoms from another, or making any Faction or Parties amongſt the people, contrary to this League and Covenant, that they may be brought to publique tryall, and receive con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne puniſhment, as the degree of their offences ſhall require or deſerve, or the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Judicatories of both Kingdoms re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, or others having power from them for that effect, ſhall judge conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>And whereas the happineſſe of a bleſſed Peace between theſe Kingdoms, denyed in former times to our Progenitors, is by the good Providence of God granted unto us, and hath been lately concluded, and ſetled by both Parliaments, we ſhall each one of us, according to our place and intereſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour that they may remain conjoyned in a firm Peace and Union to all Poſterity; And that Juſtice may be done upon the wilfull Oppoſers thereof, in manner ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the precedent Article.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49373:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>We ſhall alſo according to our places and callings in this common cauſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Liberty, and Peace of the Kingdoms, aſſiſt and defend all thoſe that enter into this League and Covenant, in the maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and purſuing thereof, and ſhall not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer our ſelves directly or indirectly by what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever combination, perſwaſion, or terror, to be divided and withdrawn from this bleſſed Union and Conjunction, whether to make defection to the contrary part, or to give our ſelves to a deteſtable indifferency or neutrality in this cauſe which ſo much concerneth the glory of God, the good of the Kingdoms, and honour of the King, but ſhall all the dayes of our lives zealouſly and conſtantly continue therein, againſt all op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and promote the ſame accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our power, againſt all Lets and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments whatſoever; and what we are not able our ſelves to ſuppreſſe or over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, we ſhall reveal and make known, that it may be timely prevented or removed; All which we ſhall do as in the ſight of God.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:49373:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>And becauſe theſe Kingdoms are guilty of many ſins and provocations againſt God, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt as is too manifeſt by our preſent diſtreſſes and dangers, the fruits thereof; We profeſſe &amp; declare before God and the world, our unfeigned deſire to be humbled for our own ſins &amp; for the ſins of theſe Kingdoms, eſpecially, that we have not as we ought, valued the ineſtimable benefit of the Goſpell, that we have not laboured for the purity and power thereof, and that we have not endevoured to receive Chriſt in our hearts, nor to walk worthy of him in our lives, which are the cauſes of other ſins and Tranſgreſſions, ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding amongſt us, and our true and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned purpoſe, deſire, and endeavour for our ſelves, and all others under our power and charge, both in publique and in private, in all duties we owe to God and man, to amend our lives, and each one to go before another in the example of a reall Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Lord may turn away his wrath, and heavy indignation, and eſtabliſh theſe Churches &amp; Kingdoms in Truth and Peace. And this Covenant we make in the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49373:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>preſence of Almighty God, the Searcher of all hearts, with a true intention to perform the ſame, as we ſhall anſwer at that great day when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed; Moſt humbly beſeching the Lord to ſtrengthen us by his Holy Spirit for this end, and to bleſſe our deſires and proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings with ſuch ſucceſſe, as may be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and ſafety to his people, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to the chriſtian Churches groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under, or in danger of the yoak of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Tyranny; to joyn in the ſame, or like Aſſociation and Covenant, to the glory of God, the enlargement of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, and the peace and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility of Chriſtian Kingdoms and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="duplicates">
            <pb facs="tcp:49373:28"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49373:29"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:49373:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49373:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49373:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49373:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:49373:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:49373:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49373:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49373:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49373:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49373:34"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49373:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49373:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49373:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49373:36"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:49373:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49373:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:49373:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49373:38"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49373:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:49373:39"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:49373:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:49373:40"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49373:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49373:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:49373:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:49373:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
